Hey everyone, welcome to this video.
Now, this video is tailored for users
who already have Open Claw installed.
And in case you haven't done so, I have
left a link above showing you how to
install OpenClaw on a Linux VPS. So,
please ensure you have OpenClaw
installed and integrated with your
preferred AI provider. So, in my case,
I'm using Gemini 3. So, I installed
OpenClaw and configured Gemini 3 API
keys to work with external applications.
So in this video we going to see how to
integrate telegram and WhatsApp with
open claw and test it out. Okay let's
get started before we get started with
the integrations with telegram and
WhatsApp. It's important that we ensure
the open claw gateway is up and running
and in good health. Now the gateway is
one of the most crucial elements in
openclaw and provides an interface
between openclaw core AI and the
messaging applications and it also
handles integrations such as telegram
bots WhatsApp and rest API calls. Now to
check the status of the open claw
gateway what you need to do is run the
command open claw gateway status and
this will provide information about the
gateway. So for example, you can see
that this is running as a systemd
service and it's enabled. So you can be
sure that it will be running 24/7. Here
you get information about the gateway
port. By default it's 18789.
You get about the path of the
configuration files as you saw earlier.
So as you can see it's listening on loop
back address here on on this part and
this is the P ID that it's running on
and everything looks okay. So we can
also confirm this by running the SS
command. So I'm going to run SS PNL TU
and then I'm going to search for open
claw using the grab command. So I'm
going to say open claw and hit enter. So
as you can see open claw is up and
running and listening on loop back
address and this is the p which is 4729
and uh this should match what we have
here 4729. So everything looks okay and
now we can go ahead and integrate
telegram and WhatsApp. In this section
we're going to look at how to integrate
telegram with open claw and the steps
are pretty straightforward and direct.
So the first step is to open your
telegram application whether on your
phone or desktop PC and search for bot
father. Now this is an automation bot
that lets you create and manage bots. So
this comes with a blue tick and at the
time of making this video has
approximately 4 million monthly users.
So once you search for bot father you
need to type forward/nebot and follow
the oncreen installation instructions.
So, this lets you choose a name and a
username for your bot. And upon
successful creation, you'll get an
autogenerated token key that you're
going to use on the command line to
onboard Telegram. So, at this point, I'm
going to pause this video and show you
what I did. So now I'm on the Telegram
desktop application on my PC and as you
can see here this is botfather which I
just explained a minute ago and it at
the moment has roughly 4 million monthly
users. So this is the first prompt. So I
typed in forward/ newbot. So it prompted
me to provide the name for the bot. So I
called it my bot. Then it requested me
to provide a username for the bot. And
in this case I chose amazing
glowbot. Now you must make sure this is
a unique name and ends with the
characters bot. Okay. Now once that is
done you'll get a confirmation message
that the bot has been successfully
created and you'll also get a link for
your bot and towards the end you'll get
a token for accessing the bot via HTTP
API. So what you need to do is to copy
this token. So I'm going to highlight it
and right click and select copy selected
text. And you'll need this in the CLI.
So join me over on the command line.
With the token ID in place, the next
step is to access the CLI and run the
command open cloud channels add. So this
will walk you through the steps for
adding your applications and Telegram is
one of them. So you'll follow the
on-creen installation instructions. So
you have to select telegram follow the
instructions and then paste the token ID
and we shall see this shortly.
So here I'm going to run the command
open claw channels add and hit enter. So
as you can see this is a list of all the
channels you can integrate with open
claw. So here you're prompted to
configure the chat channels now. So I'm
going to go ahead and select yes. So
here I'm going to pick telegram with the
bot API required. So I'm going to hit
enter. Then here I'm going to select the
default account or the primary account.
Then I'm going to hit enter. It is at
this point where I'm going to provide
the bot token. Okay. So now I've posted
my Telegram bot token. So I'm going to
scroll all the way down here and I'm
going to select finished. So I'm going
to hit enter. Then here you'll be
required to configure DM access policies
and this will allow you to pair your
telegram application with open clock.
Okay. So here I'm going to say yes and
hit enter and pairing is recommended. So
once again I'm going to hit enter. So
add display names for this account. So
at this moment I'll select no and that
is done. So as you can see the channels
have been updated. Okay. So just to
confirm this, I'm going to run the
command
open claw. So instead of channels ad,
I'm going to say channels list and hit
enter.
All right. So here, as you can see,
Telegram has been configured and the
token is okay. Okay. And I'm using the
Google default API key, the one that I
used. All right. So the only thing
remaining now is to go back to my
Telegram bot and start chatting with
Open Claw. So join me over in the
Telegram application.
So I'm back to Telegram and as you can
see I'm now chatting with my bot the one
I created earlier on. So to start I'm
going to click on start here and as you
can see OpenFlow access is not yet
configured. So this provides me with my
telegram user ID and pairing code. Now
you need to copy this pairing code here.
So I'm going to copy this and select
copy selected text. Okay. Then I'm going
back to my command line and I'm going to
approve pairing from open claw. So join
me shortly.
So I'm back on my terminal. So I'm going
to clear the screen so that we can have
some space. So now you're going to
approve pairing and to do so we're going
to run the command open claw then
pairing approve. So here I'm going to
select telegram and then I'm going to
provide the pairing code that I've just
copied. So I'm going to paste it here.
Okay. Then I'm going to hit enter.
Pairing has been successful. And as you
can see here you can see approved
telegram sender. Then you get the ID
here. So this confirms that we have
successfully added telegram on the
channels list and just to confirm this
I'm going to run the command hit enter.
Okay. So you can see telegram is here.
Okay. Also you can run the command uh
open claw status. So here I'm going to
run open claw then status
and hit enter.
Okay. So as you can see here in the
channel section telegram has been added.
So as you can see enabled on uh status.
Okay. All right. So this is show
confirmation that we have added telegram
in open claw and now we can start
chatting. Okay. So let us go back to
telegram and send a few commands and see
what the outcome is.
I'm back in telegram. So now let's start
chatting with open close. So here I'm
going to say something like, "Hey there.
Anybody home?"
And I'm going to hit enter.
All right. So here you can see we got a
reply from OpenClaw. Hey, I just came
online. Who am I? Who are you? So I'm
going to say, "Hey, I'm James."
And you are? So you can give it a name.
So here I'm going to say
uh James Cook,
uh Captain of the Seven Seas.
And here you get some confirmation. So
I, Captain James, Cook at your service.
Welcome aboard, James. Um it's good to
have a name and a chatter. I've logged
you in in my ship's manifest and hoisted
my own class. So it provides you with uh
these documents which reside in your
clot directory in the home in the root
home directory. Okay. So now since we'll
be selling together we should set the
course how do you want this ship to run.
So you can just go over this message
here. Okay. So that is it. So you can
continue chatting. So I can prompt it
and ask uh an arbitrary question. So I
can say hey captain how is the weather
like?
Okay and here it gives a report of the
weather. So this is the current location
of my VPS server. So it's at Atlanta,
Georgia. Okay. So as you can see the sky
is partly cloudy. So it gives you
temperature conditions, the wind and so
on and so forth. So you can continue
chatting with it and you can continue
prompting it to get more information. So
that was just a demonstration of how you
can configure or integrate telegram with
open claw. And as you can see we have
been successful doing this.
And finally as promised I'm going to
show you how to integrate WhatsApp with
open claw. So the instructions are
fairly simple. So what you need to do is
to go to the terminal and run the
command open claw channel z. Then you'll
be prompted to select the channels. So
here you need to select WhatsApp as your
preferred channel and scan the QR code
provided you using your smartphone. And
from there you can follow the remaining
instructions and finally you'll be able
to send messages or prompts from your
WhatsApp application to OpenClaw and
receive some feedback. So let's head
over to the CLI and run this command. So
I'm back to the terminal and I'm going
to run the command open claw channel Z
and hit enter. So once again you'll be
prompted to configure the chat channels.
So I'm going to select yes and this time
I'm going to select WhatsApp. So I'm
going to hit enter. So here I'm going to
select the default account. So I'm going
to hit enter. So here you'll be prompted
to link WhatsApp now. Okay. So here at
this point you'll be required to scan
the QR code with WhatsApp on your phone.
All right. So I'm just going to hit
enter and on your CLI screen you'll see
this QR code printed here. So what you
need to do is to take your phone and
scan this QR code which is exactly what
I'm going to do here. Okay. So I have
linked my smartphone. So I'm just going
to select link device. Okay. So as you
can see the device has been linked.
Okay. So WhatsApp asked for restart
after pairing. Okay. So as you can see
here linked after restart and uh the web
session is now ready. Okay. So here you
get more information about the access.
So here you're prompted to show whether
this is your personal number. So yes,
I'm going to hit enter to confirm my
personal number. So at this point I'll
be asked to provide my personal WhatsApp
number. Okay. So here I'm going to
provide it. Then I'm going to hit enter
to confirm it. I'm going to scroll all
the way down and press enter on this
finished option. Okay. So here we asked
to add display names for these accounts.
So I'm just going to select no. And as
you can see the channels have been
updated. Okay. So now let's list the
channels. And uh to do so I'm going to
say open claw channels list and hit
enter. So as you can see now we have two
channels. We have telegram which you
configured a few moments ago and also we
have WhatsApp. You can also run the
command open close status. So I'm going
to say open close status and hit enter.
So here on the channel section you can
see that we have two channels and both
are enabled and in our okay status.
Okay. So we have telegram and WhatsApp
configured with open claw. All right. So
at this point we have successfully added
telegram and WhatsApp. So now let's head
over to the WhatsApp application and try
to send a few messages.
As you may have noticed, there's nothing
much going on from the WhatsApp
application. We need to trigger a
message from the open clause CLI to
WhatsApp. So to do this, you need to run
this command here. So this is the
command you need to run from your
command line. Okay. So this will send a
test message from open CLI to your
WhatsApp application. So this is the
command open clone message send. Then
you specify the channel. So in this case
this is and then you specify the target
in this case your phone number starting
with the country code. So this is the
test message I'm going to send to my
WhatsApp application. So I'm going to
hit enter
and this is what you get. So as you can
see this has been sent via the gateway
and this is the message ID. So at this
point we are going to cross over to
WhatsApp and see whether we have
received this message. So I'm back to
WhatsApp web and uh as you have seen
this is a message that has come. Okay.
So I'm going to click on this and down
below you can see this is a message we
have sent from the command line. Hello
from openclaw. And at this point you can
start chatting with the the AI agent or
the AI assistant. So here I'm going to
send a message uh hi captain
how's it going? And I'll hit enter. So
I'll wait for a reply. And there you get
it. AO admiral the ship is ready the
gateway. So this is a P ID for the
gateway service. Okay. So as you can see
we have gotten a reply from
uh the AI agent. So let me check the
weather. How's the weather like?
And there you go. So this gives me the
weather update. So it gives me the
update for my current location here. So
I'm currently in Nairobi, Kenya. So this
is the weather for Atlanta, Georgia. And
this is the location of the VPS where my
Linux VPS is located. Okay. So that
confirms that the test went well and now
we can communicate with the bot from
WhatsApp.
Another thing I need to mention is that
you can also send a test message to your
telegram application from the open close
CLI. And this is the syntax. So here
I've specified the channel to be
telegram and the target this is the
telegram user ID. Okay. So you remember
the point where we generated the pairing
code. So just above the pairing code you
get your telegram user ID. So you need
to paste it here. Okay. So I'm going to
hit enter.
Okay. And as you can see from the screen
you get here hello from open close. So,
if you open your Telegram bot page or
bot account, you'll see this message,
hello from OpenClaw.
Now, when you head back to the OpenClaw
web dashboard and click on chat, you'll
be able to see a log of the messages
sent back and forth from the OpenClaw
CLI and your preferred application, in
this case, WhatsApp. So, as you can see,
this is the message I initiated from the
OpenClaw CLI. And as you can see this is
a log of everything that happened. So it
logs some of the messages to the some of
the configuration files. So as you can
see these are some of the logs and uh as
you can see here these are some of our
charts. So this is from open claw the
ship is steady blah blah blah. Okay. So
how's the weather like? So it run a few
processes to give me the weather update.
So, as you can see, it used some APIs
and it was finally able to provide me
with the weather updates. Okay, so
that's it guys for this lecture. Thank
you for coming this far. I appreciate
your support. So, in case you like this
video, please don't forget to leave a
like and subscribe to this channel to
continue getting more of these
tutorials. So from me it's goodbye and
see you in the next